Finding Aid for Arnold S. Kaufman papers, 1954-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arnold S. Kaufman papers 1954-1971
Kaufman, Arnold S. (Arnold Saul), 1927-1971
6 linear feet
85305 Aa 2
Correspondence, reports, minutes and newspaper clippings concerning his interests and activities in the Democratic Party, the National Conference of Concerned Democrats, the Eugene McCarthy presidential campaign, the New Democratic Coalition, SANE, the National Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam, the University of Michigan and national teach-ins on Vietnam in 1965; the Inter-University Committee for Debate on Foreign Policy, Students for a Democratic Society, Tuskegee Institute, and the firing of Angela Davis from U.C.L.A.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donor Number 5923.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Arnold Kaufman professed political philosophy for most of his career at the University of Michigan. Close to the Students for a Democratic Society circle in Ann Arbor, Kaufman was devoted to civil rights and antiwar struggles. In 1962, he attended SDS's founding convention at Port Huron. In 1965, he helped launch the teach-in movement. For the next six years, he worked feverishly to move the Democrats to the left, in the same manner also used by Michael Harrington. He died in a plane crash in 1971, aged forty-four.
Papers of Arnold S. Kaufman, professor of Philosophy at the University of Michigan and U.C.L.A.; include correspondence, reports, minutes and newspaper clippings concerning his interests and activities in the Democratic Party, the National Conference of Concerned Democrats, the Eugene McCarthy presidential campaign, the New Democratic Coalition, SANE, the National Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam, the University of Michigan and national teach-ins on Vietnam in 1965; the Inter-University Committee for Debate on Foreign Policy, Students for a Democratic Society, Tuskegee Institute, and the firing of Angela Davis from U.C.L.A.
Subjects:
Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-; Democratic Party (U.S.); Inter-University Committee for Debate on Foreign Policy.; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy (U.S.); National Conference of Concerned Democrats.; New Democratic Coalition (U.S.); Student Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam.; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Tuskegee Institute.; United States--Politics and government--1963-1969.; University of California, Los Angeles.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Teach-in on Vietnam (1965: University of Michigan); Vietnam.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1954-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 196T (Box 1)
  - 1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
- Political File
  - Citizens for Johnson-Humphrey at the University of Michigan 1964 (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor chapter of the Americans for Democratic Action 1967 (Box 2)
  - National Conference for New Politics 1967 (Box 2)
  - Coalition for an Open Convention 1968, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Conference for a Democratic Left 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - National Conference of Concerned Democrats 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Conference of Concerned Democrats 1967-1968, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Eugene McCarthy Presidential Campaign 1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - New Democratic Coalition
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - August-September 1968 (Box 2)
    - October 1968 (Box 2)
    - November-December 1968 (Box 2)
    - January-March 1969 (Box 2)
    - April-May 1969 (Box 2)
    - June 1969 (Box 2)
    - July 1969 (Box 2)
    - August-October 1969 (Box 2)
    - November-December 1969 (Box 2)
    - January-March 1970 (Box 2)
    - April-June 1970 (Box 2)
    - July-December 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971 (Box 2)
  - McGovern Commission on Party Reform (Box 2)
  - McGovern Presidential Campaign (Box 2)
  - Michigan Democratic Party Reform Commission 1968-1969, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Doug Crase articles (Box 2)
  - Movement for a New Congress 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Fresno (California) meeting 1969 (Box 2)
  - California Democratic party reform movements (Box 2)
  - Californians for Liberal Representation 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - George Brown for Senate campaign (Box 2)
  - South Dakota Politics, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Washington Politics (Box 2)
  - Colorado Politics (Box 2)
  - Illinois Politics (Box 2)
  - Alabama Politics (Box 2)
  - Wisconsin Politics (Box 2)
  - Jack Gore (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Political papers (Box 2)
- Peace Movement File
  - Fall-out shelters 1962, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy [SANE] 1966-1970
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Executive committee meetings (Box 3)
    - Board Minutes, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Newsletter (Box 3)
    - Reports (Box 3)
    - Reprints (Box 3)
    - News Releases (Box 3)
    - Finances (Box 3)
    - Statements, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Conscientious Objector policy (Box 3)
    - Negotiations Now (Box 3)
    - Memoranda, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - "The Big Controversy" (Box 3)
    - Miscellanea, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Dissent Magazine 1965-1970, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Marshall. Windmiller, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - National Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Vietnam Moratorium, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation (Box 3)
  - Coalition on National Priorities (Box 3)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned about Vietnam (Box 3)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Teach-in March 1965, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - National Teach-in May 1965, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence concerning the book on the National Teach-in (Box 4)
  - Manuscript of the book on the National Teach-in, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Inter-University Committee for Debate on Foreign Policy
    - Undated (Box 4)
    - 1965, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - 1966, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - 1967 (Box 4)
  - Bi-weekly Information/Action Report 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Teach-ins-Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - International Days of Protest, 1965-, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Television debate with McGeorge Bundy 1965, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Vietnam brochure (Box 4)
  - Students for a Democratic Society 1960-1968 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan Peace Research Group (Box 5)
  - Vietnam--Miscellaneous, 14 folders (Box 5)
- Tuskegee Institute File 1965-1966
  - Tuskegee Experimental Program, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Tuskegee miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Alabama Politics (Box 5)
  - Ad Hoe Committee for Justice in Macon County and Conference on Alabama Justice (Box 5)
  - Sammie Younge (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  - Ann Arbor N.A.A.C.P. (Box 5)
  - Congress of Racial Equality (Box 5)
  - Discrimination (Box 5)
  - Poor People's Campaign (Box 5)
  - Black Power, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Radical Education Project (Box 5)
  - Civil Liberties (Box 5)
  - Hope College Visiting Philosopher Program 1970 (Box 5)
  - American-Philosophical Association Committee on the participation of Blacks in Philosophy 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Student Power Movement at the University of Michigan 1966 (Box 5)
  - Report of the University of Michigan Senate Committee on Staff Excellence 1965 (Box 5)
  - Angela Davis Firing Controversy 1969-1970
    - Faculty minutes (Box 5)
    - Editorials (Box 5)
    - Letters from citizens (Box 5)
    - Kaufman writings on the Davis case (Box 5)
    - Legal documents (Box 5)
    - Resolutions, petitions and articles (Box 6)
    - Academic Senate resolution on teacher's conduct (Box 6)
    - Academic Senate-Los Angeles Division (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - U.C.L.A. Strike 1970, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Controversy over the firing of Prof. Morris Starsky at Arizona State University 1970, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Citizens for the Survival of Higher Education 1970 (Box 6)
  - U.C.L.A. Vice Chancellor David Saxon 1970 (Box 6)
  - Committee on Educational Policy 1970 (Box 6)
  - United Professors of California 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - Equal Opportunities Committee 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - Conference on the Role of the University in the Development of Peace 1971 (Box 6)
  - U.C.L.A. Faculty union, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - California Federation of Teachers 1970 (Box 6)
  - American Federation of Teachers 1970, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - U.C.L.A.-Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 6)